[SPEAKER_00]: So, you said recently, you were saying recently, that you are closer to jhāna, if you keep the precepts unbroken.
[SPEAKER_00]: And there's that... Closer than what?
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, just trying not keeping precepts... And trying to get the jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: And doing 24-hour meditation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: 24-7 jhāna, trying to do jhāna, jhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then precepts are here and there, a little bit.
[SPEAKER_01]: Kind of somewhere there, but not seen.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or not so... not even important to you, on the level of... jhāna importance.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're saying, I'll keep the precepts,
[SPEAKER_00]: Only until I feel some jhāna pleasure, and then I can...
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't have to keep precepts anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's conditional, as you say.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's that description in gradual training which says, at the end of...
[SPEAKER_00]: He keeps sīla, keeps precepts, keeps virtue, unbroken, unblemished,
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, he becomes... when he's accomplishing that, he feels the joy of being blameless.
[SPEAKER_01]: Unpolluted.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's when you... and if you don't have that joy, something's going wrong.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're not blameless yet.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's what you need to do before you can really grow any further.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, I mean, I think that the whole, like, contemporary views are just due to the fact that most people don't really read the suttas or hear the second account of them.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you read the suttas and it's just... whenever there is jhāna, it's a gradual training.
[SPEAKER_01]: It starts virtue, moderation in eating, guarding the sense doors, being watchful, composing the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Literally, the composition of the mind through restraining behavior, controlling in moderate eating, being watchful, guarding, you're composing, gathering the mind, because it's everywhere.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't see it, because it's everywhere.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, the first jhāna is that the mind has been sufficiently gathered away from the unwholesome states, away from the world, and then that internally studied, as the Buddha often described, and pleasure and joy brought from seclusion, as in secluded from these things that used to be scattered among.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that is jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you want jhāna?
[SPEAKER_01]: Start virtue, moderate in eating, guide the sense doors, be watchful, and you will have jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what the Buddha said.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if, you know, like steady your mind in jhāna,
[SPEAKER_01]: Don't erode the behavior of sensory strain, guarding the sense door, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: They brought you the jhāna, because sometimes that would happen.
[SPEAKER_01]: Monks would get jhāna, and then get overly confident, and then stop protecting the basis because of which they have jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, literally, you built a ten-story house, you're on top floor, and you suddenly start thinking that the foundations are not important, and you start messing around with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you will lose all of it, then you have to rebuild it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So,
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's where the wisdom part comes in.
[SPEAKER_01]: When you recognize, no, no, this, this remains unchanged.
[SPEAKER_01]: And this, this will make my jhāna effortless and obtainable at will, as the suttas would say.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because the whole structure remains.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if you're not necessarily abiding in jhāna at the time, the structure of jhāna is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: And when there was a, there was a sutta, I don't remember specifically, I think maybe, eh...
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm good to re-enquire, but it would encourage, eh, eh, these monks to be virtuous.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, first he said,
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you practice your precepts, and then said, you will be cultivating jhāna for a finger snap, at least, by doing that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you realize, oh, the cultivation of precepts and guarding of the sense doors is the cultivation of jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that whole sutra wasn't like, oh, he was describing jhāna, and then said, having a moment of this jhāna is very beneficial for you.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: He was describing keeping the precepts.
[SPEAKER_01]: And God in the sense does, and then he said, moment of jhāna is very beneficial for you.
[SPEAKER_01]: The one who keeps, the one who is following this instruction of gradual training, I say he's not devoid of jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is like, oh, so you're not devoid of jhāna by keeping, by being virtuous, celibate, God in the sense does.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not devoid of jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if you don't recognize it as jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because of your views of what jhāna is, you're actually doing things rightly in terms of gradual training, so you're not devoid of jhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even the joy that comes from recognizing that you are... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: ...not breaking peace.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that is already a form of samādhi.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that's already... That's already the gladness of the mind that has been unified on account of that basis.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is a unified standard of certain things you haven't done.
[SPEAKER_01]: You haven't broken the precepts.
[SPEAKER_01]: That begins to unify you in that sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: And in confidence that you will not do it, because you didn't take it conditionally so.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, yeah, that is a big problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: People would take on the precepts.
[SPEAKER_01]: And by the way, for jhāna, you need eight precepts.
[SPEAKER_01]: You won't get jhāna on account of five precepts, because you're not withdrawn from centrality.
[SPEAKER_01]: We can do a different talk on that, but that's also in the suttas, quite often mentioned.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you are, say, taking the precepts, celibate, withdrawn from sensuality, but you take them conditionally, so, you don't see that, oh, this is the development that should be protected for the rest of my life, and will elevate my mind, and I will be at will, like, I'll be able to be abiding, dwelling in jhānas at will, because the behavior is not eroded.
[SPEAKER_01]: Most people will not see it that way.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because of the contemporary views and notions of meditation, even if they take the strict precepts, it's taken conditionally so, until I get a special experience of my meditation, and then all this becomes relative.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's not.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your jhāna is there, where you keep the precepts, not when you get the special experience on account of something.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, yeah, having that unbroken precept, you can always reflect and always experience the joy.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you can direct your mind in all sorts of... not just necessarily jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have the immaterial contemplations that will result in samādhi of infinite space, infinite consciousness, neither perception nor perception, brahmaviharas, in all sorts of directions.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because the foundation remains unchanged.
[SPEAKER_01]: Withdrawal from the senses, guarding of the sense doors, taming of the mind, complete stilling of urges and cravings that you've been maintaining through acting out of them, out of lust, aversion and distraction.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's what we said.
[SPEAKER_01]: The only...
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't praise any meditation.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is the meditation I praise, and then he described jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you understand jhāna in this way we are describing it, you realize, oh, the meditation on account of guarding the sense doors and being virtuously restrained.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the meditation that the Buddha praised, because that's what jhāna is.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can use word jhāna for basically a unification of the gradual training.
[SPEAKER_01]: The first unification of the gradual training is the first jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: The second unification of the gradual training is the second jhāna, third and fourth and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, be virtuous, because you will not be devoid of jhāna by being virtuous, not by watching your nostrils.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I was like, oh, okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: Jhāna, practice of jhāna is the practice of virtue, taming the senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: Composing the mind, as I said.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, that's why in those other suttas, when people ask what meditation Master Gautama approves of, he says, this is the only meditation I approve of.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not this specific jhāna experience that people would think.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: I approve of jhāna meditation, understood in the sense of gradual training that leads you from virtue up to the moderation, seeing the danger and the satisfaction regarding the sense of seclusion from unwholesome states.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's all.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's jhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just that the joy of renunciation from from start... Oh, yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: The relinquishment is just, it's boundless joy.
[SPEAKER_00]: Cleanliness, that second, the second joy that's guarding the sense doors, sense faculties.
[SPEAKER_00]: You experience the joy of being unpolluted.
[SPEAKER_00]: Unpolluted, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Unburdened.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just clean.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're very aware in the first jhāna of everything.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thinking and pondering is there, context is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Passes there, second jhāna passes there.
[SPEAKER_01]: The world destroys.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, it's just purified experience on account of rounding up your bad behavior.
[SPEAKER_01]: Bad behavior means not necessarily heavily immoral only.
[SPEAKER_01]: It means anything rooted in greed, aversion, distraction.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a behavior that spills you over, that destroys your composition.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's polluting.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's polluting, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, rounding up, not acting out, rounding up, rounding up, rounding up, you build up a container of certain, well, energy, for the lack of a better word.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nothing mystical about it, but, you know, by refraining from this, you remain more composed here.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you never abandon virtue and guarding of the sense doors, in order to enter jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: Quite the opposite.
[SPEAKER_01]: Through confidence that comes of your guarding of the sense doors and virtue, the joy arises.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the kind of the joy, then, oh, I am unpolluted here, unwholesome states cannot get me, and that's the citta viveka.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, your mind now recognizes its own seclusion from the unwholesome states.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, the joy of first jhāna, as we said many times before, is a joy of relief.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, imagine you had a big debt hanging over your head, and now you paid it in full, and you had money left over.
[SPEAKER_01]: Imagine you were crossing a desert, worrying whether your family is still alive or not.
[SPEAKER_01]: You come back.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, they're even better than when you left them.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's a huge relief of safety.
[SPEAKER_01]: Safety from what?
[SPEAKER_01]: Safety from your own senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: They've been dragging you around.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like a ragdoll, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: Left, right, eyes, nose, assailed, left, jumping... You are just being tormented.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the only peace, a mind, that hasn't been withdrawn from the senses knows, is the peace that gets that fleeting peace through the... You know, you're dragged through the pleasant area, as opposed to being dragged through the...
[SPEAKER_01]: Either way, you have no safe.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you have no control over the senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you don't have the control of the senses, on the basis of virtue, your jhāna, your idea of jhāna, your view of jhāna, your practice of jhāna, is the extension of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Seeking pleasure through your senses, because that's the only form of peace that you know.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why you... even with that view, basically, that's why you even took the whole virtue conditionally, as I say.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you're actually still seeking the pleasure of the same kind.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not jhāna, because it's not above centrality.